A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Two Men: A Novel by Elizabeth Stoddard by Henry James 1865, AMs, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Henry James to Mrs. [George Henry] Boughton, 1888 April 10, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:26)
      His proposal hospitable and will come at 7:30 with pleasure. He wants to ask if he has any original drawings he made for Harper's. James has been asked to do an article on artists over there who ornamented those pages, and George Henry Boughton is one of them. Should like to take a squint at designs and ask him questions. What a charming portrait [Zaduna?] has made of him. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Cyril] Flower, [1888] April 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:27)
      Really a pretty present, and groups brings back happy day and delightful people. Glad an honorable accident placed him there in a sympathetic trio with her mother and her. Seems to hear Mr. G. say something ingenious regarding the Hittites or the moral beauty of the Welshman-conformists. She must have been shocked by Matthew Arnold's death as all have been, and particularly glad of the day he had lately spent with her in so happy a mood. James went to funeral. The place of burial being a charming, old English nook, but was spoiled by dreary weather. Friendliest remembrance to Lady de Rothschild. #6251-y
    - Henry James to "My dear Harton," [1888] April 28, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:28)
      Ways of Britons are not fast and furious and his invitation has just come from the Reform Club. Act upon it immediately and he will attend to renewal. Has been shut up by slight attack of pleurisy for week. Essentially better, but he should go to the Reform without James and enter boldly, mentioning his name to the porter. He will not cast him out. The first hour he goes out will look for him there; the library is a charming asylum; food is not peerless nor is it vile. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Robb, 1888 May 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:29)
      She and her husband are most munificent, and the charming eggs arrived in perfect condition. Kind that they remembered him, and hopes time not distant when he can tell them so face to face. Pheasants' eggs belong to a class of edible that he adores; he almost lives by eggs alone. What a jolly industry to produce such nice things and do such nice things to them. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Miss [Viola] Paget, 1888 May 23, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:30)
      Told she would appreciate an autograph and she is heartily welcome to the enclosed. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Henschel, 1888 June 12, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:31)
      Does not have a photograph of himself for her, but can provide a signature. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1888 July 3, ALS, 20 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 2:32)
      Happy to say he shall be able to dine with them on Friday the 13th. Thought she had achieved in her book so much reality as well as so much beauty. Most interesting to him is that she has seen a personal history in the richest and most interesting way, and it is a great success! The interest of any novel is as a view of the world, and her view is great enough. He congratulates her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mr. [Robert Underwood] Johnson, [1888] October 1, ALS, 10 pp. on 3 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 2:33)
      He wrote magnificent letter. Hasn't answered as didn't think it fair to send back the ball so soon. Has brave scruples writing him even now, and so only if he takes no notice of his barely decipherable words. His various communications interested him in only most irresponsible and irresponsive way. James is writing in odd hour of visit to the continent. Absent from London for six months or so, three of which he will spend in Paris. Wrote to Gilder answering his query about James's promised but procrastinated Daumier. Shall have it as soon as James gets back to London. Afraid it will not be as soon as then that he shall bask in luxurious moral consciousness of copyright. Sorry not feasible to treat silly Lord Sackville's silly innocence in United States as if it were only amusing. Would have finished him with own government. There is something so ugly in Bayard's coming round to a pretended horror to please the clumsy, blundering monster. Johnson's scale continues to stagger and almost scare him. He is a profuse periodical. Hopes all enterprises have brought rewards he looked for. Afraid he hasn't any London news after 15 months there without absence, except that [Edmund] Gosse has, since his father's death, discovered he is an American of high and historical degree. Johnson ought to raise his salary. Hopes he doesn't have to be ill to come to Europe, for he desires him to return. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Daniel Sargent] Curtis, [1888?] November 6, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:34)
      Talks about Curtis' social life and his own unsociableness. Abroad only to do quiet work, etc. Doesn't trust himself in cities where he is known. He begins a long serial in the Atlantic Monthly for January and little is written, so he can only have a little dip in Italy and not the Barbaro. #6251-ag
    - H[enry] James to [Daniel Sargent] Curtis, [1888?] November 18, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 2:35)
      Should have thanked him for sending awful facts. Found Genoa a good place to scribble in for the printer. Found comfort and quiet. Only in Italy a fortnight. Impossible to make a dash for Venice. Will get home by December 20. If he spends winter with concentration, maybe able to return to Italy by April 1. Then shall see him and will be removed from the odious London season. Sorry not be have seen Symonds. James not in Monte Carlo for 19 years, and finds the place exquisite, but how vulgar the stamp of modern Paris. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1888?], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:36)
      Apologizes for his long silence regarding her beautiful book [Robert Elsmere ?]. He has read two volumes and sent third to his sisters, as he had promised to write an article on Pierre Loti, and must re-read him from beginning to end. Her book has great rare beauty, and is a very distinguished production. Book abounds in life. Shall have more to say. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Messrs. Macmillan & Co., 1889 January 22, ANS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:37)
      Encloses with thanks a receipt. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [George Henry] Boughton, [1889?] June 24, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:38)
      Grateful for his invitation, but it finds him considerably embarrassed. Brother is coming from America, and tied up with others too. Sorry to miss the party. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Theodore] Child, 1890 July 4, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:39)
      Indignant at gross mutilation in this month's Harper's on the combined integrity of Daudet and himself. Moved to write a few words of disavowal to author of Port Tarascon, but Daudet should think James had a hand in inqualifiable trick. But has forgotten Daudet's number. Asks him to close and address letter. Hopes he has returned from the Antipodes. Hopes for Paris in fall if he doesn't take too much Italy now. But he can't take enough ever! #6251-c
    - Henry James to [Daniel Sargent] Curtis, 1890 July 19, ALS, 14 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 2:40)
      Address takes up one half of paper. This is rest and peace and coolness and vast violet views. Too constant perspiration to write. Wrote Mrs. Curtis from Siena, which was delightful. Returned to Florence, and started off again in quest of out of the way picturesque, but heat intense and inns dirty and he was ready to collapse at Perugia. Back to Florence until end of the month. Tells of his inn, which was a convent. Worth his while to visit; it is a good sort of place for Mrs. Curtis. James contends a man may worry through an English winter with a few precautions, but to face an English summer, the stoutest heart, constitution, and boots are required. Glad they are seeing London life. Mrs. Jack has asked him to the Barbaro. Expects to be back by August 15. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to General Seymour, [1890?] July 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:41)
      Touched by his kind invitation, and would accept if he could do what he liked. Will go to Venice August 4th for five days. Then must start for London as his leave of absence has more than expired. Sorry not to enjoy his hospitality. He is determined to come back to Italy soon, and promises to visit. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1891 February 4], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:42)
      Has engagement near Victoria Station, and tells him where to await him and then they may go easily to Mrs. Humphrey Ward's. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1891] February 11, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:43)
      Made his renewal at the Atheneum all right today. Let them dine there Friday. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1891 February 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:44)
      Would have come to her party, but goes to Paris for a month. Thanks her for her interest in all his criticism of her book. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Daniel Sargent] Curtis, [1891] June 6, ALS, 10 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 2:45)
      Tells her where he is living, and that he cannot go abroad as sister too ill to leave her. As years go on, he gets less of his beloved Italy. Life is so damnably short; always waiting for make-up years. They will certainly go to India, as they are out for all adventures. He always supposed India the greatest of all earthly impressions. Even the banality of English illusion to it has not dulled his curiosity. Envies most Prince [Ralph?]. Apropos of Princes is their incurable vulgar frivolity, as displayed in Baccaret scandal. James finds Mrs. Orr's biography of Robert Browning [Life and Letters of Robert Browning] dismal. What sticks out is that he had little life apart from his work, which drained him of distinction, but not of strength. Longs for Venice. Longs to hear that the worry of lawsuit has bored itself to death. Tells of when and how his drama will be produced in London. Will have as his heroine, Miss Robins, an American who made an immense hit in Hedda Gabler. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to [Sir John Clark], 1891 July 1, ALS, 14 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 2:46)
      Sorry about his accident. Heard rumors of his coming to London for treatment. He has been struggling through a dim London season. Hopes he has been free of the plague which is depressing. His sister declines and soon will have her release. Many friends have influenza and [John] Hay is very ill. Loveliest of Washingtonians, Mrs. Don Cameron, visited him in his den of a seedy bachelor. Speaks of other friends by name. #6251-n
    - Henry James to [Sir John Clark], [1891] December 13, ALS, 8 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 2:47)
      Called to Germany week ago by death of American friend. Will return to the peace and obscurity of De Vere Gardens. Delighted he is better. Can't do much with the Germans, who are somehow not in his line. One must really know them or leave them alone. They are ugly and mighty. Lots of future, but an intolerable present. Likes [Henry] Adams, but suffers from his monotonous pessimism. He is what he should like to have been: a man of wealth and leisure, able to satisfy all his curiosities. Wishes he could have had at Tillyponie his old friend, John La Farge, one of the most extraordinary and agreeable of men. He has been traveling with Adams, and he wonders how either could fail to murder the other. #6251-n
    - Henry James to Mrs. [George Henry] Boughton, [1891?] "Monday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:48)
      Thanks for her letter and for going to poor, dear The American, and her interest in his condition. The play is doing very well. #6251-a
    - H[enry] J[ames] to "My dear Smally" [George Washburn Smalley], [1891?] "Tuesday,", ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:49)
      The good boxes for The American have been disposed of for tonight, save one which will be returned at six and placed at his disposition. Should like to say qualifying things regarding play, especially fourth act. Has done it with all its imperfections. One of these is the sad fact that no less than four of the men are very bad: too good natured and accepted members of Compton's provincial company. They are grievous weight to carry; they give too much of the piece away. #6251-ao
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1892 January 28, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:50)
      How charming her note and how small his service. Kimloch Cooke asked him to speak of her in a page, and he took two. It is meager and trivial. Her telling him he has not been offensive in criticism is full of satisfaction to him. Has read two volumes [of The History of David Grieve] and will see her when finished with him. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1892 March 10, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:51)
      Regarding her flowers and sympathy in the loss of his sister. She was remarkable, and her death makes a great difference in his existence. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1892] March 11, ALS, 4 pp on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:52)
      A note to thank her again for her sympathy. His sister was his nearest and dearest relative. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1892] May 18, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:53)
      Committed to go to Oxford for the day, so deprives him of pleasure of dining with her, and hearing her lecture. The heart of man is an abyss. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1892?] May 20, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:54)
      No prospects in being in London for six to eight weeks. Enjoying Italy much more than he deserves. Why do they never come to Italy when he is there? #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Palmer, [1892] June 10, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:55)
      She makes him regret he is in a far country, even though he is in such a lovely one. Came to Italy a week ago, and is abroad for rest of the summer, so deprived of her hospitality. Express his regret to General Palmer. Describes beauties of Loseley. It is a dream with blue mountains without and old pictures within. He knew and loved Loseley at one time. Hopes their new house is a joy. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mr. [S.S.] McClure, [1892?] June 20, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:56)
      Out of the way when he gives him a sign. Spending summer abroad. Left London June 1st. Sorry to miss him. Would have enjoyed his report on [William Dean] Howells and [Robert Louis Stevenson]. If Osborne would only write over his own signature and not over Stevenson's. Always in London in autumn. #6251-a
    - H[enry] James to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, 1892 August 27, ALS, 6 pp on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:57)
      Sorry to be so curt regarding article on Douglas [Bounret?], but the conditions surrounding him make it difficult to write. Requires to see all of his works afresh. Doesn't know when he will be in Paris next and thus must decline. Wishes The Century wasn't so much a picture book. Excuse his blasphemies against his beautiful woodcuts. Remind him kindly to Gilder. #6251-as
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1892] "Monday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:58)
      Don't think him an uncivil brute for having kept the sacred scroll so long. He couldn't bring himself to accede to M. de Gubornatis. He hates giving autographs and signing testimonials, but didn't want to look churlish, so he waited for the gods to interfere. They haven't so he inscribed three idiotic words. Wouldn't have done so if her name had not been on page. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. Pruyn, [1893?] May 22, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:59)
      Kind of her to send him a copy of Frank Peabody's address on good old Doctor, which he though remarkably eloquent and of perfect veracity. Writes from spot where such good New Englandisms seem too far away. On way, reluctantly, back to London after three months abroad. Usually fights to be shy of it during June and July, but this year has to sacrifice to obligation. Almost congratulates her at not being there as usual. Pleasure at Boughton's to talk to you of old Albany names and memories. #6251-d
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1893] June 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:60)
      Pleased to accept for June 17. Nothing to swagger about, but to be the confident of her achievements. Shall try to persuade her that her human defaillances don't matter. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893 June 28], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:61)
      Out of town; sorry to miss him. London quiet now with its complication, as impossible time in Rome in the spring turned out to be. Never got to Italy though spent three months abroad. Regrets not meeting his daughter, but as he is placing her in England, it is only a pleasure postponed. Doesn't expect him at James' sordid seaside. Hopes for his speedy return at a calmer hour. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893] July 3, ALS, 10 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:62)
      Glad to hear from him even though painful duty devolves on him. His sending Marchesa Theodoli's little proverb and his plea for it do a real honor to the high principal of sympathy within him. The greater pity that the case should not be intrinsically for him. Virtue never deserves attention: it only deserves paradise. Madame T. may get a slice of latter for her little play, but she would be ill-advised to bid for the former. The little art is much more difficult and special than she can suspect. These would not be a ghost of a chance that this little piece or anything like it should reach the footlights. No woman should ever write a play because it hasn't the scenic quality. There is no chance for one act things. Hates to have to say such things. The lady's novel was very pretty, and she will do that sort of thing more profitably. Glad of his reappearance. Talks of the Swiss and the French, and his early summer at Lucerne. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893] July 14, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:63)
      Brewster is a Gallo American in all the force of the term, for he combines the grand idiosyncrasies of both types (his failure to give an address and his faith in the Swiss post). Sorry Brewster came and didn't see James. He has stuck fast to the squalid shore, refreshed by its climate. Glad Brewster will return in October. Will be in London then. Delighted to hear of his book and watches for it. Has he read Le Dottine Pascal which he has just lain down? #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Glendower]Evans, [1893] September 4, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:64)
      Sees by paper Ceslialonia reached Boston, and supposes she will have called Cambridge according to her intention. Hopes there will be no delay in receiving an answer. Regrets not being able to help her. Leaves town for three weeks, but send word if he can do more. Will be in Whitby, Yorkshire. Envies her the lovely Lynton. #6251-aq
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893 October 11], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:65)
      Shall be delighted to see him. Come to lunch Friday if he is free. Pleasantest way to see him. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Humphrey] Ward, 1893 October 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:66)
      How shall he dress up his inability to undertake the job regarding Browning, which he does him the honor to propose? It would be insurmountably difficult to give the time. He is more pressed and preoccupied than he has ever been in his life. Sorry, because project would be full of charms. He is flattered to be asked, and glad of his wife's progress. She will be better when the child is born. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1893] October 18, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 2:67)
      Has kept relics of Marcella [by Mrs. Humphrey Ward] longer than he meant to, but now returns. Read with liveliest interest. She is only British Romancer he can read. Doesn't count Robert Louis Stevenson as he is Scotch. It is a rich and luminous chronicle. Found it absolutely interesting, in spite of things he doesn't conciliate fondness for. It's a lovely novel he desires to keep her up to the mark, and up to the market. Excuse his crudity. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893] October 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope and enclosure. (Box-folder 2:68)
      James claims the enclosure came from a heartless tradesman, accompanying his manuscript. Will show it at the earliest opportunity to Heinemann or through him to Gosse. Doesn't know how the question of shortness can be gotten over. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893 November 3], ALS, 7 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:69)
      No good news from him. Gosse assures him no use in offering any publication of a manuscript less than 50,000 words. His manuscript contains at the most 15,000 words. English magazines want 6-7,000 words. Slender physique of his little offshoot a grave obstacle to place it. Suggests how he can add dialogues, etc. Nothing would induce him to shoot with Brewster save reflection he would kill Brewster first. Charming of him to see something in The Lessons of the Master. His slow journey to Rome suggests pleasure. P.S. Since registered mail will not reach him in time, he is sending proofs in ordinary form. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mr. and Mrs. Pemberton, 1893 [December 25], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:70)
      Thanks for remembrance and cordial wishes for present and future peace and plenty! #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Henry Bennet] Brewster, [1893] "Monday,", ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 2:71)
      Remind him again of his real address, which he has lost, so he may name a day Brewster can visit him. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, [1893] "Wednesday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:72)
      Has been in Paris for last two months. Leaves for Lucerne, and will be back in London in June, but in some burrow in the country where people are not, but doubts if it is anywhere on the globe! Will miss her hospitality. Hope she is near her last rehearsals. When back he will knock on the stage door. Hopes she is sound and safe. Blesses her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Miss [Grace] Carter, [1894] January 26, ALS, 10 pp. on 3 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 2:73)
      Appreciates her reaching Venice so soon. Wired to see if he can help her. Doesn't know why Miss Woolson [Grace Carter's sister] died. Mrs. Benedict's cable was a bolt out of the blue. Wants to hear of need before he comes. American Consul is one who could help. Funeral in Rome. Sends heartiest sympathy. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Miss [Angelina] Milman, [1894 January 26?] "Friday,", ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:74)
      Excuse his involuntary silence. Not able to see her this p.m. Had sudden call to go to Venice because of friend's death, and one of his servants fell dangerously ill. So worried that he could not write her sooner. May not have to go to Venice and will see her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Miss [Grace] Carter, 1894 February 2, ALS, 12 pp. on 4 l. with envelope and typed transcript. (Box-folder 2:75)